Jas Sohi

Data Analyst

contact@jassohi.com

Summary

Hi, my name is Jas as in "Jazz" music! I'm a problem solving, big picture thinker, and team player with a strong technical background; I'm a logical thinker who works well with data and who always uses the appropriate technology to aid in decision making. I'm very adaptable and considered by many as a jack of all trades; however, I also know the value of specializing. After 5 years of experience in Sales & Operations seeing the potential to use operational data to make better decisions, I discovered my passion for Data Science and decided to pursue learning full time to prepare for a career change. Coursera: In January, I received the 10th and final certificate as part of the Johns Hopkins Data Science Specialization after completing the capstone project in the R and Python programing languages (which is showcased on jassohi.com). I was one of the few to complete all courses with distinction (mark > 90%). Udacity: Never one to stop learning, I joined the 1st ever cohort of Udacity's Data Analyst Nanodegree. When I graduate, I will have completed 5 interesting projects throughout the entire Data Science pipeline from Data Wrangling to Data Visualization. I went above and beyond in the first 2 projects and was offered the position of Code Reviewer! Specialties: Data Analysis, Business Process Improvement, Inventory Management, Forecasting, Web design, Information Systems, Programming, Business Intelligence Programming: R, Python, HTML Databases: MongoDB, MS SQL Server, MySQL

Experience

Udacity Code Reviewer at Udacity

March 2015 - Present (4 months)

Being part of Udacity's 1st ever Data Analyst Nanodegree cohort, I was selected to be one of the very first Udacity Code Reviewers. I review student project submissions (Python & MongoDB) and do both a thorough code review as well as a project evaluation. I strive to give actionable and helpful feedback to students while also improving my code reviewing skills.

Supply Chain Coordinator at BuildDirect

August 2013 - November 2014 (1 year 4 months)

\$250k warehouse to warehouse transfers budget managed by optimizing transfer requests. # Over 20 smartsheets created to improve processes and ensured quality control/data integrity (Only 1 of 3 within the company granted privileges to create sheets). # Led the inventory administration team of 5 to ensure the analysts could focus on their core competencies: analysis and supplier relationship management. # Reduced ETA delays significantly (from avg of > 30 to nearly 0 a day) by putting in place checks & balances leading

to satisfied customers who received product on-time as per their estimates. # Designed and implemented the container tracking smartsheet to replace inefficient email processes

3 recommendations available upon request

Inventory Management Analyst at BuildDirect

May 2012 - August 2013 (1 year 4 months)

Managed inventory for 2 of the largest 9 categories (Tiles & Engineered Wood Flooring). Responsibilities included forecasting, replenishment, reconciliation, data analysis, & supplier communication. # Established new Inventory Department under the lead of the COO # Introduced time-tracking system for task visualization which helped department scale effectively. # Recommendations made to improve the product launches from a holistic point of view.

Inside Sales Representative at BuildDirect

October 2010 - May 2012 (1 year 8 months)

Ensured customer satisfaction by helping customers throughout the entire purchase cycle. #85% of customers rated my customer service from good to excellent. #\$150k in revenue for best month of May 2012 #\$1.1 million added to top line growth in 2011 in a product category (Tiles) known for low minimum order sizes, lower than average margins, and long lead times before closing. #Highest amount of daily phone touches with potential customers

2 recommendations available upon request

Senior Sales Consultant at Bell Mobility

August 2008 - October 2010 (2 years 3 months)

100% score on a mystery shop (only 2nd out of 9 employees). # 9 months of exceeding targets & green in all metrics (activations, warranties, & accessories). # \$43,500 added to bottom line with 145 activations in 2009. # 200% to target for postpaid sales in August 2010 due to strong work ethic. # As a key holder and senior consultant, trained new employees.

1 recommendation available upon request

Census Enumerator at Statistics Canada

July 2006 - August 2006 (2 months)

Took a list of addresses/phone numbers and contacted citizens, by phone or directly (door to door), urging them to complete their 2006 Census forms.

Projects

Predictive Text Web App Using Bag-Of-Words Model - R (Shiny) & Python (N-gram model)

December 2014 to Present

Members:Jas Sohi

A large corpus (text from twitter, blogs, web sites) was used to train a predictive model. The N-grams model was done in Python, the web application in R using Shiny framework.

Analyzing the NYC Subway Dataset - Python (NumPy, Pandas, ggplot) & Tableau

January 2015 to Present

Members:Jas Sohi

Rainy weather => more subway usage? The analysis was done in Python (NumPy, Pandas, ggplot) and the visualization in Tableau. Result: statistically significant difference, but not large enough to postulate causality.

Data Wrangling with MongoDB - Python (PyMongo), MongoDB, & R (R Markdown)

February 2015 to Present

Members:Jas Sohi

Cleaning OpenStreetMap.org data for a Vancouver region using data munging techniques, e.g. assessing validity, accuracy, completeness, consistency, and uniformity. The cleaning was done in Python, data was stored in MongoDB (using PyMongo). Results were analyzed and reported using R Markdown.

Skills & Expertise

Data Analysis

Inventory Management

Business Process Improvement

Customer Service

Microsoft Excel

Business Intelligence

Supply Chain

Leadership

Forecasting

R

Python

SQL

NoSQL

MongoDB

Tableau

XML

Bash

Github

Git

Pandas

Poker

Negotiation

Marketing

Google Analytics

Project Management

Statistics

Teamwork

Pivot Tables

Web Design

Wordpress

Joomla

Logistics

Inside Sales

Google Adwords

Adobe Creative Suite

HTML + CSS

cPanel

Writing

Vlookup

QlikView

Task Management

Machine Learning

Databases

Smartsheet

Highly detail oriented

SQL Server Management Studio

Web Analytics

ERD

Database Design

HTML

Education

Simon Fraser University

BBA, MIS, Finance, and Entrepreneurship, 2004 - 2009

Activities and Societies: BASS Yearbook Team, BLAH weekly intramurals, Finance Club, MIS Club, & Punjabi Student Association

Certifications

Data Science Specialization - 9 Certified Courses + Capstone Project

Coursera Verified Certificates License 7RdAH4nkEe December 2014

Intro to Data Science

Udacity January 2015

Data Wrangling with MongoDB

Udacity February 2015

Data Analysis with R

Udacity April 2015

Intro to Machine Learning

Udacity April 2015

Certified Supply Chain Professional

APICS August 2013

Courses

BBA, MIS, Finance, and Entrepreneurship

Simon Fraser University

Data and Decisions I BUEC 232

Introduction to Computers and Information Systems in BUS 237

Business

Information Analysis and Systems Design

Event Driven Programming - Visual Basic

Management Support Systems

Managing Data Communications

BUS 362

CMPT 110

BUS 462

BUS 492

.....

Independent Coursework

Digital Analytics Fundamentals Analytics Academy

Google Analytics Platform Principles Analytics Academy

BCIT - Relational Database Design and SQL - 88%

Grade

CMPT 1630

MongoDB for Python Developers M101P: MongoDB University

try-sql Code School

Languages

English

French (Limited working proficiency)

Punjabi (Native or bilingual proficiency)

Honors and Awards

Outperformed S&P 500 in Investors of Tomorrow Stock Market Competition (2008) Vancouver Sun Run 2011 Time 1:16 Vancouver Sun Run 2012 Time: 1:09 Vancouver Sun Run 2013 Time: 57:58 Grouse Grind June 2013 53:00 Tough Mudder - Whistler 2013 Finisher - with a dislocated shoulder:) SeaWheeze Half Marathon - 2:31 2014 BuildDirect Charity Poker Champion Tough Mudder - Whister 2015 - TBD

Interests

Hiking, Skiing, Ball Hockey, Rollerblading, Working Out, Basketball, UFC, Video Games, Computers, Hockey, Electronics, Bollywood, Motorcycles, Hiking, Comedy Shows, Gadgets, Podcasts, Mobile Phones, Financial News, Running, Xbox, Red Bull, Diet Coke, Floatation Tanks, Personality Types (INTJ)

Test Scores

CMPT 1630 - Midterm

June 2014 Score:91.58%

This exam was based heavily upon understanding database modelling concepts as opposed to just SQL coding.

Volunteer Experience

Great Canadian Shoreline Cleanup at SFU Alumni

June 2013 - June 2014 (1 year 1 month)

Jas Sohi

Data Analyst

contact@jassohi.com



6 people have recommended Jas

"Jas is the consummate professional who knows how to drive operational improvements with passion, intelligence and clear communication. Jas and I worked well together at BuildDirect building the inventory department and developing new processes for the company. His proven track record of successful projects was made possible by his broad knowledge and cross functional expertise within operations, sales and marketing, make Jas a pro-active contributor, any organization would be fortunate to have as part of their team. I can highly recommend Jas for a variety of operations, logistics and IT positions."

— Jim Hourigan, managed Jas indirectly

"Jas Sohi was a pleasure to work with, he is thoughtful, engaging and consummate team player. Jas was instrumental in the evolution of the inventory replenishment department at BuildDirect. He developed processes that focused on adding value and removing waste. He was willing to continually go above and beyond to accomplish any task or project that was assigned. A few highlights of his time at BuildDirect are as follows: 1 - Improved a lot of inefficient and manual processes to reduce redundant work such as the Container Tracking smartsheet 2 - Managed the smartsheet implementation and created dozens of smartsheets and reports to support optimized processes 3 - Tested, implemented and oversaw the fresh desk ticketing system 4 - Standardized and implemented jargon such as WETA and SETA so all departments spoke the same language "

— Jason McMurdo, CPC, managed Jas

"Jas is detailed and process oriented person, with in-depth knowledge of Supply Chain and Inventory Management. He is passionate about his work and always get things done. Working with Jas has been a pleasure and easy task, bringing his A game every time. He has helped Inventory team @ BuildDirect gaining significant data, process improvement, overall reaching great results and becoming one of the best teams in the company. His training and leadership was always innovative and inspiring."

— Mack Raicevic, worked directly with Jas

"Jas placed and managed a large order for me. He did a great job helping me get the order on time as I had various contraints with contractors. Subsequently I needed to place a further order and Jas recognized

me, quickly assessed my needs and was creative in helping address them. In addition to being reliable and creative, Jas is also very personable. It was a pleasure working with him."

— Suresh Bhatia, was Jas's client

"Jas Sohi has been one of the most intelligent and reliable Sales Representatives in the BuildDirect sales team. He is a consummate professional who consistently receives excellent feedback from clients due to his ability to manage their expectations and communicate with them effectively regarding their sales orders. One of the key things that impresses me about Jas is that he is still able to generate over a million dollars of revenue to date for his product lines that are known for having lower margins and longer lead times, a feat that is considered challenging for a Sales Representative in his position. He also demonstrates excellent time-management skills while providing great customer service, evident from the high volume of clients he interacts with on a daily basis. Furthermore, his passion for technology is apparent through proposing ideas to improve business processes and maximize productivity for the company. He is considered an "A" player at BuildDirect, and I firmly believe he is one of the most productive Sales Representatives in the team."

— Rodney Noriega, Sales, Business Development, BuildDirect, worked directly with Jas at BuildDirect

"I am proud to say that I have worked with Jas during my time as a sales consultant at Bell Mobility. Jas is a very focused worker that ensures that all things that needs to be "done" gets done. He is a person you can rely on for specific and measurable information. I look forward to seeing his success in the future."

— **Keith Wong**, Senior Sales Consultant, Bell Mobility, worked directly with Jas at Bell Mobility

Contact Jas on LinkedIn